A Guide to the Betty Harrington MacDonald, Alexandria Ship Records, 1732-1861 [bulk, 1783-1825], 1973-1989
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Betty Harrington MacDonald, Alexandria Ship Records 1732-1861 [bulk, 1783-1825], 1973-1989
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
218-219
4 boxes (1.25 linear feet)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Betty Harrington MacDonald, 1985-1989.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of data that Betty Harrington MacDonald gathered concerning ships that entered and exited Alexandria, Virginia during the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. Among the information are names, weights, and home ports of the ships. Two folders (Box 218, folders 13 and 14) contain information about Alexandria-born slaves, and two folders (Box 219B, folders 1 and 2) contain information about Alexandria-born sailors. Box 218, folders 17 and 18 contains a paper, Alexandria, Virginia, May 1774 - December 1783, which chronicles key occurrences in the city. Box 219A includes an alphabetical card index of Alexandria seamen from the 1820s-1860s. The first half of the collection is from two notebooks titled Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria. They primarily contain information about cargo.
Arrangement
Subject, as imposed by donor. Folder titles were also imposed by donor. An exception is Box 219B which required a restoration to subject order.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Miller, T. Michael, Artisans and Merchants of Alexandria, Virginia, 1780-1820. Bowie, MD: Heritage Books, 1991; Vol. 2, p. 333.
MacDonald, Betty Harrington, Port of Alexandria in A Composite History of Alexandria. Alexandria, VA: Alexandria Bicentennial Commission, 1975.
Locations of Originals
Most of the information was copied from original documents housed in the National Archives in Washington, D.C., the Library of Congress in Washington, D.C., or the Public Records Office in London, England. The contents of Box 219B were taken from crew lists, Port of Philadelphia at the National Archives.
Index Terms
Sailors - Virginia - Alexandria; Ship registers - Virginia - Alexandria; Shipping - Virginia - Alexandria; Ships - Cargo - Virginia - Alexandria
Contents List
- Notes from Public Records Office - London, 1732-1815; 1974. (Box-folder 218:1)
- Notes from Public Records Office - London, 1768-1773; 1974. (Box-folder 218:2)
- Notes from Public Records Office - London, 1768-1773; 1974. (Box-folder 218:3)
- Notes from National Archives Ship Documents - Alexandria Documented Vessels, 1812-1820; 1973. (Box-folder 218:4)
- Notes from National Archives Ship Documents - Alexandria Documented Vessels, 1815-1820; 1973. (Box-folder 218:5)
- Notes from National Archives Ship Documents - Alexandria Documented Vessels, 1818-1824; 1973. (Box-folder 218:6)
- Notes from National Archives Ship Documents - Alexandria Documented Vessels, 1821-1825; 1973. (Box-folder 218:7)
  Not in box, 6/22/2007.
- Notes from National Archives Ship Documents - Alexandria Documented Vessels, 1823-1825; 1973. (Box-folder 218:8)
  Not in box, 7/14/2008.
- Notes - Alexandria Documented Vessels, 1789-1810, 1812-1915. (Box-folder 218:8A)
- Notes - Alexandria Documented Vessels, 1891-1907. (Box-folder 218:8B)
- Notes from Library of Congress - Philadelphia Complete Counting House Companion, 1785-1787; 1978. (Box-folder 218:9)
- Notes from Alexandria Gazette, 1785-1812. (Box-folder 218:10)
- Notes from Alexandria Gazette, 1784-1813. (Box-folder 218:11)
- Notes on vessels from Index of U.S. Merchant Vessels, National Archives, 1810-1907; 1978-1979. (Box-folder 218:12)
- Notes on Alexandria-born slaves (1 of 2), 1791-1812; 1975-1979. (Box-folder 218:13)
- Notes on Alexandria-born slaves (2 of 2), 1791-1812; 1978-1979. (Box-folder 218:14)
- Notes on ship Hunter, 1789-1815. (Box-folder 218:15)
- Notes on John McKnight, 1802-1809; 1975. (Box-folder 218:16)
- Alexandria, Virginia, May 1774 - December 1783 (by Alexandria Bicentennial Commission), 1971. (Box-folder 218:17)
- Alexandria, Virginia, May 1774 - December 1783 (by Alexandria Bicentennial Commission), 1971. (Box-folder 218:18)
- Notebook from Stabler-Leadbeater store, 1847-1848; 1983. (Box-folder 218:19)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1803-1806; 1974-1975. (Box-folder 218:20)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1803-1806 [1801-1802]. (Box-folder 218:21)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1803-1806 [1803]. (Box-folder 219:1)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1803-1806 [1804]; 1975. (Box-folder 219:2)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1803-1806 [1805]; 1975. (Box-folder 219:3)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1803-1806 [1806]; 1975. (Box-folder 219:4)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1807-1815 [1807]; 1975. (Box-folder 219:5)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1807-1815 [1807]; 1973. (Box-folder 219:6)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1807-1815 [1808]; 1973. (Box-folder 219:7)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1807-1815 [1809]; 1973. (Box-folder 219:8)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1807-1815 [1810]; 1975. (Box-folder 219:9)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1807-1815 [1811]; 1975. (Box-folder 219:10)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1807-1815 [1812]; 1975. (Box-folder 219:11)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1807-1815 [1813]; 1975. (Box-folder 219:12)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1807-1815 [1815]; 1975. (Box-folder 219:13)
- Notebook - Inward Manifests, Port Alexandria, 1807-1815 [1815]; 1975. (Box-folder 219:14)
- Alphabetical card index of Alexandria seamen, 1820s-1860s. (Box 219A)
- Alexandria Born Seamen, 1789-1819. (Box-folder 219B:1)
- Alexandria Born Seamen, 1821-1861. (Box-folder 219B:2)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Alexandria, 1804. (Box-folder 219B:3)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Bethsey (Betsey), 1801. (Box-folder 219B:4)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Betsy, 1793. (Box-folder 219B:5)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Diana, 1805. (Box-folder 219B:6)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Fabius, 1802. (Box-folder 219B:7)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Fair American, 1806. (Box-folder 219B:8)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Federalist, 1806. (Box-folder 219B:9)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Henrietta, 1805. (Box-folder 219B:10)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Hope, 1801. (Box-folder 219B:11)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Hunter, 1802-1917. (Box-folder 219B:12)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Jacob, 1805. (Box-folder 219B:13)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Julia, 1804. (Box-folder 219B:14)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Mary Ann, 1810. (Box-folder 219B:15)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Paulina, 1800-1803. (Box-folder 219B:16)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Snow Rachel, 1802. (Box-folder 219B:17)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Rebecca, 1806. (Box-folder 219B:18)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Romeo, 1803. (Box-folder 219B:19)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Two Brothers, 1809. (Box-folder 219B:20)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Union, 1800. (Box-folder 219B:21)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Union, 1809. (Box-folder 219B:22)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - Virginia, 1793. (Box-folder 219B:23)
- Alexandria Documented Vessels - William and John, 1810. (Box-folder 219B:24)
- Port of Alexandria, cargo lists. (Box-folder 219B:25)
- Port of Alexandria, list of seamen. (Box-folder 219B:26)